"Naturally Boosting AMPK
with Caloric Restriction for Life Extension"
In my book on everything
evidence-based in weight loss,
How Not to Diet, I had a section
entitled "Amping AMPK."
AMPK is an enzyme that acts
as a universal fuel gauge
for plants and animals,
revving up
when it detects a depletion
of the universal fuel.
The universal energy currency
in all of biology
is a molecule called
adenosine triphosphate,
commonly known as ATP.
The tri in triphosphate means
three, as in tricycle or,
in this case,
ATP's three phosphates
where energy is stored.
Plants make ATP
with energy from the sun,
and animals make it
by burning fat,
carbohydrates, and protein.
The energy is spent
by releasing the phosphates,
which transforms ATP to AMP,
adenosine monophosphate,
with mono meaning one,
which then can be juiced up
with two more phosphates
back to ATP,
and the cycle continues.
In this way,
every cell in our bodies
and in every living thing
is like a little
rechargeable battery.
AMP molecules are charged up
with phosphates to ATP
using sunlight or food
and then drained back down
to AMP
to do the cell's work.
This brings us to AMPK,
or AMP-activated protein kinase.
A kinase is a type of enzyme.
What might be the function
of an enzyme activated by AMP?
A buildup of AMP
means the rechargeable battery
is running low.
It's akin to the fuel gauge
in your car reading empty.
As the needle creeps toward
the E, what do you do?
Add more fuel.
But instead of having
an extra gas can in your trunk,
you may have junk
in the trunk,
fat stores on your body.
So that's what AMPK does:
It flips the switch
in your body
from storing fat
to burning fat.
That's why AMPK
is not only known
as the "master energy sensor"
in our body
but the "fat controller."
No wonder I featured it
in How Not to Diet.
But it can also control aging,
and so also plays
a starring role
in How Not to Age.
To sustain life,
each of our cell "batteries"
needs to stay fully charged.
This means maintaining a ratio
of about 100 ATP for every AMP.
So, our body needs
to perfectly balance
cellular activities
that consume energy
with cellular processes
that generate energy.
In times of plenty,
our cells can plow
full steam ahead.
However, in lean times,
which for animals
means not enough food,
and for plants
means not enough light
(darkness is like starvation
for plants),
AMPK kicks in
to reorient the cell
into conservation mode
and start tapping
into our energy stores,
like burning off body fat.
Our cells can also institute
a recycling program
called autophagy.
Autophagy comes from the Greek
words auto, meaning "self,"
and phagein meaning "to eat."
So, autophagy literally means
"self-eating."
It's a housekeeping process
by which defective
cellular components
like misfolded proteins
that had been allowed
to wastefully build up
in times of surplus
are broken down and scrapped
for spare parts.
This doubles as both salvage
operation and quality control,
scavenging raw materials
in scarce supply,
as well as clearing away
some of the buildup
of damaged debris
that is implicated
in the aging process.
As one review put it,
"The janitor
is the undercover boss."
This is one of the reasons
AMPK is increasingly recognized
as a pro-longevity factor.
AMPK induces autophagy,
which cleans house,
sweeps away accumulated waste,
and effectively institutes
a sort of cellular "reset."
There are three main ways
longevity researchers
establish an aging pathway:
Does the factor worsen with age?
If you amplify it,
does it accelerate aging?
And if you dampen it,
does it slow aging,
and thereby extend lifespan?
The loss of AMPK activity
as we age
fits all three criteria.
Our levels of AMPK drop
as we grow older,
and it gets harder to activate.
When this decline
is exacerbated,
aging is hastened (at least
in the hearts of mice).
And when this process
is reversed,
when AMPK activation
is boosted,
lifespan is extended
in model organisms,
as much as 38 percent
in a type
of microscopic roundworm
known as C. elegans.
Up and down
the evolutionary tree of life,
one of the most reliable ways
to extend lifespan
may be long-term
food restriction.
And AMPK activation is thought
to be one of the mechanisms
for this longevity boost.
What was remarkable about
the AMPK boosting experiments,
though, is that animal lives
can be extended
even though they were allowed
to eat as much as they want.
So, AMPK activators
can effectively fool the body
into thinking it is starving,
flipping it into
protective housecleaning mode
without having to suffer
the pangs of deprivation.
AMPK activators
can thereby be considered
calorie restriction mimetics,
or imitators.
No wonder AMPK is considered
a "druggable" target
for longevity.
But is there a way we can
naturally boost AMPK activation
to slow aging
without starving ourselves?
The answer is yes,
which we'll explore next.